Guide to the Vladimir and Véra Nabokov publishing correspondence, 1945-1977.
Nabokov, Vladimir and Véra publishing correspondence, 1945-1977
- Series I. Outgoing Correspondence from Vladimir Nabokov 1947-1975
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, October 19, 1963. (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Not addressed, in French, explaining how much he liked Girard's translation of the first part of the poem that opens Pale Fire, and wanting to know what is going on with the film rights to Laughter in the Dark. Exasperated note in pencil asking why VN cannot simply say what it is that Irving Lazar wants.
  - TL to Monsieur Raymond Girard from Vladimir Nabokov, October 19, 1963. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Not addressed, in French, regarding Girard's translation of the first part of Pale Fire, including several explanations of terms that have confused the translator. Particularly interesting is VN's discussion of "homer" and the joke that eludes Kinbote as it probably will most French readers. Explains impossibility of including translator's notes in the French edition, as these may be confused with Kinbote's notes. Possibly a copy that was enclosed with 2-34.
  - Typed corrections sent to Raymond Girard by Vladimir Nabokov, October 19, 1963. (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Typescript of corrections (in French) to Canto One of "Pale Fire" (in Pale Fire), translated by Raymond Girard. Page 1. Possibly a copy that was enclosed with 2-34.
  - Typed corrections sent to Raymond Girard by Vladimir Nabokov, October 19, 1963. (Box 2, Folder 37)
    Typescript of corrections (in French) to Canto One of "Pale Fire" (in Pale Fire), translated by Raymond Girard. Page 2. Possibly a copy that was enclosed with 2-34.
  - Typed corrections sent to Raymond Girard by Vladimir Nabokov, October 19, 1963. (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Typescript of corrections (in French) to the Canto One of "Pale Fire" (in Pale Fire), translated by Raymond Girard. Page 3. Possibly a copy that was enclosed with 2-34.
  - TLS to Vladimir Nabokov from Maurice Coindreau, January 6, 1964. (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Written from Paris, in French, outlining Coindreau's objections to VN's suggested mode of work. Accepts those corrections that right concrete mistakes and inevitable interpretive errors, but refuses to consider "inadmissible modifications" that either do not translate what VN has written, are "barbarisms" (i.e. are not French words) or will make readers laugh. Provides some instances of suggested corrections by VN that do not (in Coindreau's opinion) translate the original text but interpret or embellish. Writes that at the age of 71, C. is not about to allow "obscenities". Discusses duties of author to translator, and vice versa. Touches briefly on difficulty of undertaking a 'team' translation (Girard and Coindreau are translating the text together). 4 pages, photocopy, with pen and pencil annotations by VN.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, January 7, 1964. (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Not addressed, in French, concerning list of corrections to the for the most part excellent Cannac translation of an unidentified work (perhaps The Defense?), and assures Ergaz that Dmitri's health is continuing to improve.
  - TLS to Monsieur Maurice Coindreau from Vladimir Nabokov, January 14, 1964. (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Writing from Palace Hôtel, Montreux, in French, VN delivers a lengthy (and sarcastic) response to Coindreau's queries. Explains that if Coindreau (now translating Pale Fire) has methods of translating, so too has VN for working with translators. Objecting to the tone of C.'s letter as "unfriendly and quite uncalled for", VN asserts that the modifications he suggests are not meant to replace an incorrect phrase with one that is correct, but are intended to make phrases more exact or clear, and 'reminds' C. that the only method he has for expressing his thoughts is in language, and not by sign or"a little dance like that a bee performs to notify its fellows of the results of its honey-gathering." Responds to C.'s queries one by one, and argues in conclusion for his own right as author to suggest corrections. 5 pages, including 3 page typescript of corrections to Kinbote's "Commentary", translated by Coindreau.
  - Typed corrections sent to Maurice Coindreau from Vladimir Nabokov, January 14, 1964. (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Typescript of corrections to Canto Two of "Pale Fire" (in Pale Fire), translated by Coindreau. 3 pages. Probably sent with 2-40. Pencil annotations, including drawing of what "neon-barred" looks like.
  - TL to Vladimir Nabokov from Madame D. Ergaz, January 24, 1964. (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Written from the Bureau littéraire D. Clairouin, 66 rue de Miromesnil, Paris, in French, concerning the translation of Pale Fire by two translators (Girard and Coindreau).
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, January 29, 1964. (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Written from Montreux, in French, acknowledging receipt of January 24 letter, and refusing to write to Coindreau as Ergaz desires until C. has responded to VN's letter of January 14. Asks that future installments of the translation be copied for VN as he likes to make notes on his copy of the translation.
  - Signed autograph to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, May 9, 1964. (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Written on Palace Hôtel letterhead, Montreux, in French, complaining of possible defamation. Has read in the Italian journal L'europeo words attributed to Gallimard: (roughly) "VN, a capable writer who has yet brought nothing original to literature." Would like Ergaz to find out if Gallimard did in fact say this, and proposes a course of action either way.
  - TL to Michel Mohrt from Vladimir Nabokov, January 19, 1965. (Box 2, Folder 46)
    Written from the Palace Hôtel, Montreux, in English, expressing on the whole delight with the Girard/Coindreau translation of Pale Fire, which he says is "certainly the finest I have ever been given." Notes some "incredible blunders", and insists that his corrections be taken into account, rather than dismissed as the examples of VN's "special brand of French", or at least that he be given the last word in which rendering will appear in the final version. "I have sufficient French to know more exactly than [C.] when his French does not correspond to my English."
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov (1), with typed corrections for Pale Fire (2), January 19, 1965. (Box 2, Folder 47)
    (1) Not addressed, in French, explaining the enclosure. It is snowing, and the Nabokovs both have colds. (2) Typescript of corrections for the Girard-Coindreau translation of Pale Fire, included suggestions for the Index, which has not yet been translated (or at least seen by VN). 34 pages. Pencil annotations, including illustrations.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, January 29, 1965. (Box 2, Folder 48)
    Written from the Palace Hôtel, Montreux, in French, expressing great disappointment that Ergaz will be unable to translate The Gift by reason of ill health, and asking whether the "irascible" Coindreau and his "companion" will want to take over the translation.
  - TL to Madame Marie Schébéko from Vladimir Nabokov (1), with typed corrections for Pale Fire (2), September 30, 1965. (Box 2, Folder 49)
    (1) Written from the Palace Hôtel, Montreux, in French and English, concerning the translated text of Pale Fire. Wonders whether a note might not be added explaining that it was VN who devised the word-games for this French version, and drew attention to mistranslations: "As an old goalkeeper I am a little surprised that nobody has thanked me for the many saves I have made." Reiterates impossibility of notes for this particular novel. Adds that the texture of this translation "is a marvel, a masterpiece, limpid, stylish and taut. It is a great compliment to my novel, and I am very grateful." (2) Typescript of corrections "made on page proofs of Feu Pale." 5 pages. Some pencil annotations.
  - TLS to Madame Marie Schébéko from Vladimir Nabokov, November 19, 1966. (Box 2, Folder 50)
    Written from the Palace Hôtel, in English, concerning the translation of The Eye and The Gift. Writes that if Mohrt thinks Magnane's translation of The Eye reveals a perfect knowledge of English, "he has another think coming". Cautions Ergaz to put matters more gently with Mohrt.
  - TLS to Monsieur Claude Gallimard from Vladimir Nabokov, October 10, 1967. (Box 2, Folder 51)
    Written from the Palace Hôtel, Montreux, in French, thanking Gallimard for his kind invitation to Paris for the launching of The Gift (in French) but apologising that any interruptions may deal a fatal blow to his current project. Concluding 'politesses.' Photocopy.
  - TL to Madame Marie Schébéko from Vladimir Nabokov (1), with typed additions and corrections for Pale Fire (2), November 13, 1967. (Box 2, Folder 52)
    (1) Written from the Palace Hôtel, Montreux, in French, explaining the enclosures, and asking Schébéko to take care of these matters. (2) Note to be included in the French translation of Pale Fire, identifying VN as the translator of rhymed poems and word games. List of errata.
  - TLS to Madame Marie Schébéko from Vladimir Nabokov, April 28, 1969. (Box 2, Folder 53)
    Written from the Palace Hôtel, Montreux, in English, accepting Gallimard's offer for King Queen Knave, warning that Ada must fetch a much higher price, and discussing a minor contract matter involving Lolita.
  - TLS to Madame Marie Schébéko from Véra Nabokov (1), with contract for Ada (2), October 18, 1969. (Box 2, Folder 54)
    (1) Written from Montreux, in English with some French, discussing in detail the contract for Ada. Marked in pen, pencil, and black felt. (2) Contract for Ada (draft). Marked up and annotated
  - TL to Georges Magnane from Vladimir Nabokov, December 30, 1970. (Box 2, Folder 55)
    Written from the Palace Hôtel, Montreux, concerning Magnane's translation of King Queen Knave, with suggested corrections for misinterpreted words or sentences, imprecise words, repetitions, translations of poems, "tutoiement", and requesting the elimination of the "postface." Urges that Magnane ameliorate VN's own suggestions where possible, but take their intention into careful consideration.
  - TL to Charles Orengo from Vladimir Nabokov, September 24, 1971. (Box 2, Folder 56)
    Written from Palace Hôtel, Montreux, in English, discussion Chaïns translation of Ada, on the whole with admiration at the texture, rhythm, vocabulary, and Chaïns' resourceful puns, but noting some general principles of correction. Discusses "method" by which VN is to transmit corrections.
  - TL to Charles Orengo from Vladimir Nabokov, July 28, 1972. (Box 2, Folder 57)
    Written from the Palace Hôtel, Montreux, in English, 'regretting' the dangerous operation and long convalescence undergone by Orengo, acknowledging the difficulties faced by the translator of Ada but placing himself at the disposal of the latter, and refusing to consider seeing the French publication of Mary before the much more important Ada. Will be happy to see Orengo in Switzerland.
  - TL to Charles Orengo from Vladimir Nabokov, August 28, 1972. (Box 2, Folder 58)
    Written from the Palace Hôtel, Montreux, in English, containing a "list of errors and inaccuracies" found in the typescript of the French translation of Mary, deploring its carelessness, and expressing the hope that Orengo still intends to visit Switzerland.
  - TLS to Madame Marie Schébéko from Vladimir Nabokov, January 7, 1974. (Box 2, Folder 59)
    Written from the Palace Hôtel, Montreux, preferring, on the basis of samples, Donald Harper to Blandenier as translator for Transparent Things. Wishes S. a happy new year.
  - TLS to Madame Marie Schébéko from Véra Nabokov (1), with two statements (2) & (3), and a memorandum (4), October 21, 1974. (Box 2, Folder 60)
    (1) Written from Palace Hôtel, Montreux, in English, discussing the contract status of various works ( Bend Sinister, Look at the Harlequins!, Lolita, Gogol). Expressing sympathy for Schébéko who, having recently lost a "close friend", must attend to "several matters within a stretch of time hardly sufficient for one." VN is grateful that Schébéko intends to continue representing him. (2) Statement of royalty account from Oisterwijk. Dated July 30, 1974. Photocopy. (3) Statement of account from Prins & Prins. Dated April 9, 1974. Photocopy. (4) Draft memorandum of agreement between VN and Circulo (Brazil). Annotations in pen and pencil.
  - TLS to Madame Marie Schébéko from Véra Nabokov, with two statements, October 21, 1974. (Box 2, Folder 61)
    Photocopy of 2-59.
  - TLS to Madame Marie Schébéko from Vladimir Nabokov, October 2, 1975. (Box 2, Folder 62)
    Written from the Palace Hôtel, Montreux, in English, informing the "gentlemen" that he has assigned "all of my right, title and interest" in the works listed on the second page to Dmitri Nabokov. All notices, statements and payments are "to be addressed to and in the name of: Mr. Dmitri Nabokov, c/o Mrs. Vladimir Nabokov" or other such address as D. may designate. List of works with publishers: Gogol, The Gift, Laughter in the Dark, Despair, The Defense (all French editions). Note in felt: "rec'd Nov. 17. 1975."
  - 8 Telegrams to D. Clairouin from Vladimir Nabokov, 1959-1971. (Box 2, Folder 63)
    Regarding contract negotiations for publication and translation of Lolita and Gogol,
- Series II. Lolita Correspondence between Olympia Press, Clairouin, and Vladimir Nabokov
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press and the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, June 6, 1955 to December 26, 1955. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    10 items (4 TLS from Girodias, 5 TL from various parties, including carbon of letter sent by G. to VN). Charts beginning of relationship between G. and VN, and of Lolita's early publication history. Concerns the signing of contracts, G.'s suggestion that VN eliminate French phrases in the novel (7.1.55), the French publication of Lolita., and G.'s early claim that he may not be able to register copyright in France (9.27.55).
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, and the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, March 20, 1956 to March 28, 1956. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    5 items (2 TLS from Girodias, 3 TL from Clairouin), regarding the search for an American publisher for Lolita.. G. asserts his right to negotiate the contract but claims that he will do nothing without informing VN. Ergaz notes VN's new hopes that Lolita. will be published in the US (he had not so hoped before), but explains that she has written to VN asking about the impact of any controversy on his position as university professor.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Vladimir Nabokov, June 6, 1956 to March 12, 1957. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    14 items (3 TLS from Girodias, 9 TL from various parties, 2 statement). Various financial transactions and accountings, as well as discussion of translation rights. Two letters from Girodias to VN (probably copies sent to Clairouin) outlining G.'s position with regard to VN's intention of finding an American publisher for Lolita, particularly in light of the copyright question and possible legal difficulties (11.12.56 & 3.12.57). G. reminds VN that Olympia took an enormous risk in publishing the novel, and that all current interest in Lolita. is due to the important first publication (3.12.57).
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Vladimir Nabokov, March 20, 1957 to May 17, 1957. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    9 items (2 TLS and 1 signed autograph from Girodias, 5 TL from various parties). Regarding the French translation of Lolita as well as some financial matters. Three letters from G. to VN (probably copies sent to Clairouin) discussing the status of negotiations with American publishers, and finally breaking off communication. G. asks whether VN would consider accepting reduced royalties (4.11.57), and explains his wish to search out a "firm of secondary importance" with whom to publish a joint edition (5.6.57). Stresses that VN has nothing to fear from G (5.6.57) but finally writes to Ergaz in exasperation that he must cut short such a "sterile" dialogue" (5.17.57).
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Vladimir Nabokov, August 8, 1957 to November 8, 1957. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    11 items (5 TLS from Olympia and 6 TL from various parties). Includes a copies of letters sent from G. to VN answering various accusations (about the price of the book relative to VN's royalties, and about the sending of statements), refusing to acknowledging the rupture of their contract, and expressing G.'s sense that he is a "victim of your personal problems." Other letters concern translation and financial matters, including the search for an American publisher for Lolita.. Ergaz (11.8.57) acknowledges the unfortunate state of G.'s relationship with VN, and hopes VN will take G.'s demand that Olympia be mentioned in all editions of Lolita. (10.29.57) in the "right way."
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press and the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, November 20, 1957 to December 31, 1957. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    9 items (5 TLS, 4 TL and a statement) charts the escalation of the dispute between VN and G., as G. threatens to publish (in opposition to VN's express wishes) an American edition of Lolita under Olympia's imprint and in conjunction with an American firm (11.20.57), while accusing VN of acting in bad faith (both towards Ergaz and Girodias). G. tells his side of the story and describes Putnam's offer for Lolita. Ergaz expresses irritation with VN, but wonders why G. insists on threatening VN, as their interests are the same, and conciliation would seem the only solution (11.29.57).
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, and the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, January 2, 1958 to January 31, 1958. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    6 items (2 TLS, 4 TL), regarding dispute between VN and G., with G. attempting to explain his actions (sending the check for the "derisory" sum of Fr 178, for example), claiming that he is not looking to quarrel. VN is by now refusing to accept G.'s checks.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press and the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, February 6, 1958 to March 24, 1958. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    6 items (4 TLS and 2 TL). Discussing financial matters, including VN's decision to accept more royalty payments from Olympia.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press and the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, March 28, 1958 to May 16, 1958. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    6 items (3 TLS and 3 TL). Concerning financial matters as well as G.'s demand that mention of the original (Olympia Press) edition in all translations of Lolita. Ergaz writes that while VN is happy with Kahane's translation, a rare occurrence (4.1.58), he has categorically refused this demand, which G. claims has nothing to do with VN anyway (3.28.58 & 5.16.58). Mention (5.16.58) of new legal difficulties ahead for G.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press and the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, July 21, 1958 to October 22, 1958. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    12 items (4 TLS, 6 TL, 2 statements). Concerning translation matters, the selling of translation rights in Japan, Finland, Britain, Italy and Spain, as well as South America. Includes letter from Clairouin with list of books and authors published by Weidenfeld.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press and the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, November 7, 1958 to December 31, 1958. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    7 items (2 TLS, 4 TL, 2 statements). Concerning the litigation surrounding Lolita and Olympia (11.7.58), rumors of a split between VN and Olympia (11.14.58), a pirated Polish serial edition of Lolita being published in Israel (12.5.58), and the continuing "cold war" being lobbied by the Nabokovs.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press and the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, January 1959. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    7 items (4 TLS, 3 TL), tallying up sales for the past year (1958), concerning the Swedish contract (1.13.59), as well as the contract with Weidenfeld. G. offers Ergaz the sum of Frs. 500 000 for the "many sacrifices that you have had to make in order to craft an agreement with M. N." (1.5.59).
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press and the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, February 4, 1959 to February 20, 1959. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    12 items (6 TLS, 5 TL, 1 statement, with 2 carbon copies of letters sent by Girodias to Steimatzki). Concerning the contract dispute between Olympia, VN, Steimatzki and Putnam's. VN suddenly withdraws consent to a deal with the Israeli firm of Steimatzki, a deal that G. claims he had reservations about, and that is already signed by 2 of 3 parties. G. assures Schébéko that his firm is one that fulfils its obligations (2.10.59) and warns Steimatzki that, based on G.'s experience, Putnam's is unlikely to reconsider its objections to Steimatzki's plan of reproducing the Putnam edition of Lolita (2.12.59). Mention of VN's preference for the Putnam edition.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press and the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, March 6, 1959 to May 11, 1959. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    7 items (3 TLS, 4 TL). G. asks after the status of negotiations with Mondadori (3.5.59). Schébéko compiles list of foreign language contracts. Brief return to Steimatzki problem (3.13.59), but moving on to a new issue: the inclusion in the Olympia edition of Lolita of Olympia's foreword, which VN takes as an unauthorized addition to his text, and therefore prohibited by his contract with Olympia (4.15.59). G claims that the foreword (concerning legal matters) is his prerogative, especially given a recent interview by VN misrepresenting (according to G.) Olympia's role in the publication of Lolita. (4.29.59 & 5.11.59).
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press and the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, May 20, 1959 to August 11, 1959. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    8 items (3 TLS with autograph calcuations attached to 8.6.59, 3 TL, 1 autograph note, 1 statement). List of translation contracts (6.19.59) and discussion of various financial/accounting matters (including a bill for The Black Diaries of Roger Casement).
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press and the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, September 3, 1959 to September 7, 1959. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    3 items (1 TLS, 2 TL). Concerns the "Open Letter" that Girodias would like to see signed by Graham Greene, Ernest Hemingway, John Steinbeck and William Faulkner. G. solicits Schébéko's help, but she is reluctant to press these writers. Includes 7 copies of the "Open Letter".
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press and the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, September 7, 1959 to November 9, 1959. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    9 items (3 TLS, 6 TL). Concerning various translation and accounting matters. More trouble with Steimatzki (though of a lesser variety).
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press and the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, January 6, 1960 to January 30, 1960. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    8 items (3 TLS, 3 TL, 1 statement, 1 autograph draft dated 1.20.60). Concerning financial matters, particularly the method of paying Olympia the sums owed from translations of Lolita. Girodias objects to VN's claim that their original contract makes no provision for down-market editions of Lolita, and to VN's refusal to send copies of contracts involving translation rights to G (1.19.60). Note from Schébéko deploring VN's bad faith.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Odette Hummel February 2, 1960 to March 8, 1960. (Box 3, Folder 19)